

Kavitha S Ph.D. Seed Science

And Technology

Contact

Address

141A, Mathur (via), Oddappatti (vill & Post), Pochampalli Taluk, Krishnagiri, Tamil Nadu 635203

E-mail

kavithasowmiyaseedtech@gmail.com

Skills

Classroom presentations

Advanced

Student records management

Advanced

Lecturing

Advanced

Student counseling

Advanced

Assistant Professor with one year of experience successfully contributing to Seed Science and Technology curriculum development and delivery. Driven to contribute to program outcomes by facilitating engagement and supporting learning objectives. Enthusiastic professional with background in academic advisement.

Work History

2014-03 - Junior Research Fellow

2014-08 GOI-DUS scheme, TNAU, Coimbatore

Implementation of PVP legislation through DUS

testing under ICAR and SAU systems

2017-12 - **PMFBY Staff**

2018-07 ADA office, Krishnagiri

 Worked as a PMFBY Staff in the "Pradhan Mantri Fasal Bima Yojana" Crop insurance scheme at the ADA office, Krishnagiri

2018-07 - **Assistant Professor**

S. Thangapazham Agriculture College, Vasudevanallur, Tenkasi District

- Built strong rapport with students through class discussions and academic advisement.
- Revised course objectives, course materials, instructional and assessment strategies for SST 201
 Principles of Seed Technology (2+1), SST 301
 Seed Quality Regulation and Storage (1+1), EXP 401 Commercial Seed Production (0+5) and CRP 101
 Fundamentals of Crop Physiology (2+1) courses.
- Mentored students and communicated internship and employment opportunities.

Education

2009-08 -2013-06

2019-05

B.Sc.: Agriculture

Adhiparasakthi Agricultural And Horticultural

College

OGPA: 7.79

Advanced Performance improvement	2016-09	Agricultural College And Research Institute - TNAU, Coimbatore OGPA: 8.84
Student research guidance Advanced	2019-08 - 2023-08	Ph.D.: Seed Science And Technology AC&RI, Tamil Nadu Agricultural University - Coimbatore OGPA - 8.41
Languages	Thes	is title & Specialization:
Tamil and English		 a) M.Sc. Seed Science and Technology i) Title of thesis: 'A Comparative study of Accelerated Ageing and Natural Ageing in Maize, Black gram and Sesame' ii) Specialization: Seed Storage b) Ph.D. Seed Science and Technology i) Title of thesis: Development of Herbal based formulation for enhancing the storability of pulse seeds. ii) Specialization: Seed Storage
	NET (Qualification
		Cleared ASRB NET - 2019 in Seed Science and Technology with 51.1 %
	Publi	ications
		 Kavitha, S., C. Menaka, S. Srinivasan, A.Yuvaraja. 2017. Accelerated Ageing Test in Maize: Pattern of Seed Deterioration. Madras Agricultural Journal. 104(1-3): 41-44. Kavitha, S., C. Menaka, M. Ananthi. 2017. Deterioration in sesame (Sesamum indicum L.) seeds under natural and accelerated ageing. International Journal of Chemical Studies 5(4): 1141-1146. Kavitha, S., C. Menaka, M. Ananthi. 2017. Comparative study of physical, physiological, biochemical and histological changes due to

2014-08 -2016-09

Grading

M.Sc. : Seed Science And Technology

- **accelerated and natural ageing of blackgram seeds**. International Journal of Chemical Studies. 5(4): 1969-1973.
- Kavitha, S., J. Renugadevi, P.R. Renganayaki, M. Suganthy, P. Meenakshi, K. Raja, K. Madhan.
 2023. Comparative phytochemical profiling of Psophocarpus tetragonolobus (L.) D.C. seed extracts for effective storage of cowpea seeds.
 Legume Research: 1-9.
- Kavitha, S., J. Renugadevi, P.R. Renganayaki, M. Suganthy, P. Meenakshi, K. Raja, K. Madhan.
 2023. Phytochemical profiling of Erythrina variegata leaves by Gas Chromatography-Mass Spectroscopy. Agricultural Science Digest: 1-9.

Conference

- Poster presentation in the National conference on "Climate Smart Agriculture for Livelihood Security: Challenges and Opportunities" held at Anbil Dharmalingam Agricultural college and Research Institute, Tamil Nadu Agricultural University, Tiruchirapalli (2019).
- Poster presentation in the 6 th AGSC 2020 under the theme "Multi-Dimensional Approaches inTransforming Agriculture" at TNAU, Coimbatore.
- Poster presentation in the 7 th National Youth Convention 2022 under the theme "Food Security to Nutritional Security: Youth Perspective" at TNAU, Coimbatore.
- Tamil conference Kavitha, S., C. Menaka, M. Ananthi. 2017. Accelerated ageing test in sesame: pattern of seed deterioration. ISBN: 978-93-9731-29-0.
- Participated in the International e conference on "Recent Developments for Sustainable agriculture" held at Faculty of Agricultural Sciences, Bharath Institute of Higher Education and Research, Selaiyur, Tambaram (29 th June 2020), Chennai.

Seminars

- National Symposium on Entrepreneurship
 Development for Life Sciences E D Bioz'13, 23 rd
 January, 2013, ACAS, P.G. & Research
 Department of Biochemistry Kalavai, Vellore.
- National Seminar on Mushrooms Rise of Research and Retreats for Humanity 30 th September, 2019, Department of Plant Pathology, TNAU, Coimbatore
- Seminar on Understanding Plant-Virus Interaction to Identify Novel Antiviral Weapon in The Plant Arsenal, 2020. Bioingene.com

Trainings/ Workshops

- Participated in the International training cum Workshops on "Seed Testing for Quality Assurance" under the aegis of Indo-German Cooperation on Seed Sector Development held during 07-10 March, 2022 and organized by TNAU, Coimbatore and ICAR-Indian Institute of Millets Research, Hyderabad.
- Two days Workshop in "Advanced Statistics for Technical Enhancement in Agricultural Research Workshop" during February 27-28, 2020, TNAU, Coimbatore.
- Two days Workshop in "Big data Analytics for Agricultural Sciences" during February 10- 11, 2020, TNAU, Coimbatore.
- Participated in "Technical Writing Skills Workshop" on February 8, 2020, TNAU, Coimbatore.
- Participated in "Career Planning Workshop" on February 7, 2020, TNAU, Coimbatore.
- Participated in "Stress Management Workshop" on March 10, 2020, TNAU, Coimbatore.
- Completed online Interdisciplinary Short Term
 Course on Basics of Organic Farming from May 31 to June 06, 2020, Department of Botany and IQAC, Athalye-Sapre-Pitre College, Maharashtra.

References

(i) Dr. J. Renugadevi

Professor (Seed Science and Technology) Agricultural Research Station, Tamil Nadu Agricultural University, Bhavanisagar – 638 451.

(ii) Dr. G. SRINIVASAN

Professor and Head, Cotton Research Station, Srivilliputthur.